hello I'm your host David Bernard
today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
cat state of subscription apps report
each episode in this series will explore
one crucial metric and share actionable
insights from Top subscription app
operators with me today Greg Stewart CEO
of ladder on the podcast I talk with
Greg about why optimizing for user
success drives more Revenue than
conversion hacks how to maximize the
impact of annual plans and why relying
too heavily on discounts is a trap hey
Greg it's nice to have you back on the
podcast looking forward to chatting
today thanks for having me awesome to be
here we're huge fans of the podcast and
glad we could do it again so one of the
big sections in the forthcoming report
is LTV and so we're going to share all
sorts of stats around what we see
patterns we see in different cohorts in
different segments and different time
frames of how our customers are
monetizing their users how do you as one
of the fastest growing fitness apps out
there right now how do you think about
LTV yeah we we don't spend a ton of time
thinking about LTV as a metric for a
couple of reasons and then we'll talk
about what we do look at but LTV for us
is a little too wishy-washy and too
macro to make decisions on like you you
think about LTV and you're looking at
some of your oldest cohorts the product
was different many things changed by the
time you've got a good read
on anyone cohor the entire picture could
have changed so it's not close enough to
real time to help inform the decisions
of the business we manage the day-to-day
business on Payback period which is a
far cleaner very tangible metric that we
can talk to the entire team about we
invest in our growth that growth gets
payback over time we understand the cash
flow Dynamics and that we're what we're
able to pay and invest in based on the
expectation on when that investment is
recruited
so far more real time from a growth
perspective instead of LTV we spend a
ton of time thinking about retention
obviously this is an extremely consumer
oriented retention minded team and
business and and app and that's been
true from the beginning Fitness is easy
where there's a natural retention metric
which is workouts if you don't start a
workout you can't complete it if you
don't complete workouts in ladder you're
not going to join you're not going to
continue on as a member everything that
we build every feature that we
contemplate inside the app is all aimed
at incremental workout completions it's
all aimed at keeping you around the app
keeping you motivated to continue on and
stay consistent with your plan that as a
metric looking at workouts is far more
tangible and easier to predict kind of
the outcome of what's happening at the
user level versus thinking about LTV
High workouts equals High LTV so these
things lead to LTV as an output metric
but really hard to control input metrics
when you're just anchoring to what in
value I love that you brought this up
and maybe some people are listening like
well why did Revenue cat then do a whole
section of their report on LTV but I
think that's actually kind of key to
properly contextualizing what LTV is so
even though you don't think of it in
terms of LTV you are measuring payback
period a revenue cat we have a chart and
you probably look at this dayx realized
LTV is kind of what we call it so you
can check into different points like 30
days you know how much revenue you've
realized from that cohort yeah like we
are looking at that and that is payback
period right at the end of month one at
the end of month three at the end of
month six at the end of the year how
much has been recouped are you
profitable on that user that unit so we
are certainly staring at that lifetime
value in terms of what is that customer
worth over the three years that they've
been a member we have a estimate and a
number there but it's just not doesn't
give us the ability to make any decision
around it so it's just not practical
from a day-to-day management of the
business we do spend a ridiculous amount
of time kind of understanding retention
at various kind of points in our
customers journey and it all starts with
who's coming into the app like we spent
a lot of time defining at a very granual
level who are the relevant personas for
ladder and the programs that we have we
called them teams teams are led by a
coach each one of those teams represents
a unique Persona a unique workout style
that we are speaking to directly in
Creative that's aimed at that particular
audience so we're very very focused on
speaking to the right user users that we
know are more likely to find success and
long-term success with ladder even
before they're in the app and we use the
quiz which we talked about in the last
podcast which collects a handful of
questions to understand the fitness
profile of a lead coming through how
many workouts doing what modalities they
like what equipment they train with
where they want to work out and we have
a really good sense in real time who's
coming through our funnel and we cater
to multiple personas and we can see that
in real time on one side of the spectrum
we have Pilates influenced at home with
a dumbbell with a lot of women who are
newer to strength on the other side we
have advanced gym goers full access to
equipment and machines they know what
they're doing when they show up and
they're looking for an easier way to
plan the workout itself so very very
different person
that we're speaking to uniquely in
different creatives on social platform
so step one is getting to the right
people and really making sure that you
understand the pain points and how our
solution addresses those pain points at
the Persona level and the quiz and our
marketing is all all geared towards that
in the app itself we have a 7-Day free
trial we intentionally don't ask for a
credit card upfront which we didn't know
was unique when we launched turns out
it's pretty pretty unique we just had a
hunch that like as a consumer oriented
team it's a better experience we
launched the business in the middle of
Co there was an app being built every
single day in our space it was very hard
to stand out to the capital markets it
was very hard to get the consumer
attention and we knew we had a superior
product from very early on in our life
cycle as a business so we wanted to
create a entry point into the app with
little to no friction like let's use the
product to move people through the
funnel to do the selling to work people
through one or two workouts then
ultimately if that happens the
likelihood to pay is is very high so we
use the product to convince not getting
them to pay and then hoping that
something happens after the fact so we
spend a ton of time and continue to
spend time iterating on that experience
of what happens when you come into the
app what's the first thing you see how
do we get you through the first workout
in the right program as quickly as
possible how do we get you through a
second workout how do we introduce these
features that aren't typical in fitness
apps we have chats and social oriented
experiences that are in other apps like
us so we have to figure out the right
moments to introduce these experiences
and to make sure that we don't overwhelm
Our member who's coming in with some
context but not committed yet on lud as
a solution for them so the trial is
really really important and we can we
can pretty accurately predict what will
happen from a conversion perspective we
week one workouts perspective month one
retention perspective based on how the
trial starts the level engagements the
number of workouts that they're
completing and that continues on into
the into the membership week one is an
incredibly important kind of fork in the
road for us you know we're solving for
three workouts per week per member and
most of the Iration is happening around
that first week if you're hitting that
metric in the first week the odds of
doing it again the second week are
exponentially higher the odds of
retaining at theend into one month if
you're a monthly member are very high
and so we use workout completions both
in activation in first week and then
beyond to understand the retention
profile of our members and to understand
the retention profile of cohorts of
users that are coming in over time in
that first week you've already collected
a ton of data to understand kind of what
Persona you have and then you start
seeing kind of the early signals of
potentially being a good fit how deep
does this like segmentation and
customization go are you showing
different pay walls are you showing
different offers how deep do you go with
that segmentation to get people to that
place where they are going to start
paying not on the happy path so if you
come in off the quiz you download the
app you start a trial you start
completing workouts we're not really
trying to optimize or configure the pay
wall against what's happening most of
our happy path conversions are happening
in the first two weeks post trial
expiration where we do segment on
workouts and offers is if folks don't
commit and don't convert right after the
trial and we do have a significant
number of people in anyone coworth that
will convert down the road because
Fitness is very personal and just
because it wasn't relevant today it
doesn't mean you won't have a need come
spring summer fall the following January
so we have lots of shots at bat with our
leads to convert them over time and
we'll think about offers and coupons and
the right mix of urgency levers based on
the number of workouts that they
completed in trial as a proxy for how
much context they have coming in if you
haven't completed a first workout you
really don't understand what ladder is
you don't understand the concept of a
team that it's programming that it's
Progressive overload trading that it's
not a library of workouts you're on a
team you don't know if it's the right
team or not so we have to both configure
that experience when they do pay to
someone who has very little context but
even before that we need to Market to
that user knowing that they're not sold
yet on the core value prop itself how
does that play out I know you've been
and I think we talked about this either
in person one time we were hanging out
or maybe even on the last podcast that
you've been shifting a lot of your
subscribers from monthly which is what
you used to kind of promote more to
annual as a way to increase that LTV so
in the report we're going to be sharing
like 14-day LTV and 60-day realized LTV
so how are you thinking about that kind
of balance between monthly and annual
and getting those payback periods
reduced yeah our payback periods are
very very very tight and we've over time
increased the penetration of annual
members in our subscriber race which has
been exciting the first rev of that was
on price and that was a bunch of testing
and iteration and then we got to a place
where we thought we had the right
clearing price for folks that were
willing to commit upfront and then we
did some experimentation around the pay
wall anchoring to annual putting
incentives and added features into the
annual membership to entice folks to
commit on longer time frame and then
when we are close to the end of a trial
for any user and you actually have
completed a workout we'll first
introduce the annual offer is a hey did
you know you know there's a cheaper way
on a monthly basis to purchase ladder
you get a significant discount you get
added features and you're committing
yourself to a year which is good for
motivation and and accountability so
certainly something that we've spent
time on and not it's now more annual
members in our subscriber base than
monthly and that wasn't true the time we
talked so in that segmentation are you
presenting the monthly to certain
cohorts and the annual to others or are
you now more focused on that annual
product and trying to drive as many
users as possible to that annual or the
fact that it is a kind of bigger
one-time commitment do you do you have
to kind of find that happy balance both
I would say for folks that complete zero
workouts in trial we don't push annual
the context isn't there we expensive
versus must apps in our space you don't
know enough on why the price is the
price and why it's worth the value
versus what you're solving for so for
zero workouts we point to monthly for
those that have gotten through kind of
key activation moments first workout
second workout will introduce and
socialize and lean into annual right
before trial expires and right after
trial expires if that offer isn't taken
or the conversion doesn't happen then we
start moving to monthly offers but the
monthly offers are all intra offers
they're just a discount on the first
month that then clicks up to full price
on month two so it's to lower the hurdle
to get into the product and to really
experience it in the first couple weeks
of membership and then it clicks up to
full price after that are you making
those same kind of offers to those folks
who didn't complete a workout I think I
saw a promo it's like $5 or $10 or
something for that first month do those
people that you offer that $5 offer to
are they less retentive than the people
who were willing to kind of jump in and
pay off the bat important point I I
would make is if you stacked up all the
time on iteration between activation in
the product and using our product and
levers that we know are correlated to
workout completions versus iteration on
deals it would probably be 90% product
10% deals so we spent a lot of time
moving the needle on the percent of
people that get through one workout the
percent of people that get through two
workout and the conversion rate is
extremely high for folks F that get
through those moments so we have a lot
of atypical levers in our app versus
fitness app and I give you an anecdotal
story is we have a feature where you can
cheer on other folks who are working out
you open the app on the home screen
you'll see avatars on the top you'll see
a yellow Vault Circle and it represents
how far is the workout that person is
and you can send them a cheers by double
tapping and pick an emoji that you want
to send seems very simple but we
correlated the number of Shear receive
to workout completions and long-term
retention and so we realize the
importance of this feature and people
feeling like there are others that are
doing it with them and feeling
supportive that we now use that to
figure out how do we incentivize and
increase the number of outbound shears
that on the receiving end you're more
likely to receive a basket of shears in
your experience especially early on in
the trial so we spent a lot of time
thinking about what are the levers that
we have to drive incremental workout
completions that ultimately get people
to the value prop of ladder of having a
plan and ultimately help convert them or
increase the likelihood that they'll
convert so most of our brain space has
gone towards that we do have built-in
kind of moments in our calendar where
deals are more compelling than not we'll
spend a little bit more time thinking
about the iteration side of that we
program workouts on six we Cycles we
call them string series and they become
like these great entry point moments
into the product where you can tell us
story about urgency saying you weren't
here or it didn't make sense for you to
join for the first string series but
tomorrow is day one and it's a great
time to hop in and we have a whole
motion from a marketing perspective
through the plot for mobile through our
coaches in the app all telling a story
about the next series what we're working
on what themes are at the platform level
that gives us the ability to then go
into our database and tell a story on
urgency and use discounting and coupon
to lower the barrier to entry to
incentivize people to get in experience
the value prop so we have moments where
it's more impactful to experiment on the
deal side the $5 deal is a good good
example where folks who claim or take
advantage of the $5 offer it's only
about half of those that are retained in
month two and it's pretty consistent now
this is the minority of conversions the
small basket of conversions is folks
that didn't get through the product in
the trial but of that group about half
are retained but that half clicks up to
full price so they go five to
$29.99 so the first month it's a really
nice spike a user growth and in the
second month it's growth in ARR for that
cohort even though it's a smaller basket
of users that make it through the first
month all right Greg thank you so much
for uh all those insights anything else
you wanted to share as we're wrapping up
I would say if you want to see some of
the learnings in real life that we just
talked about especially in trial and
activation I would try yeah there's a no
credit card trials we talked about so
very easy to get in there and I think if
you get through that first work out the
odds of us seeing you as a number are
very high so would love to have
everybody try the product and let us
know what you think awesome we're going
to see a lot of like super fit
subscription app folks next
year well Greg thanks so much for
joining me this it's a great
conversation they appreciate it thanks
for having
me thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review and
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private community
[Music]